Mariana Villamil Sastre

Curriculum Vitae

Personal information

email mariana.villamil@etu.unige.ch

Personal planetmariana.github.io

website

Professional profile

Astrophysics master student with specialisation in exoplanetology. With background geodynamical problems applied to extra solar planets, data analysis and observational techniques. Strong interest in planetary geophysics. Proven experience in scientific programming, writing and discussion. Very proactive person, with rapid learning skills and new ideas to collaborate in different work environments.

Education

2021-Current MSc. Astrophysics, Astronomical Observatory of Geneva, Switzerland.

2016-2020 BSc. in Geosciences, University of Los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia.

2014-2019 **BSc. in Physics**, University of Los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia.

Awards

2021 Colombian Ministry of Science and Foundation COLFUTURO scholarship, Grant of \$50.000 USD to start a science-related Master program outside Colombia.

Research experience

2022-Current Modeling the tectonic regime on Earth-like exoplanets, (Master thesis), The objective is to run simulations in 2D in order to study the main parameters involved in the tectonic regime for different core/mantle ratios in Earth-like exoplanets, Advisor: Dr. Emeline Bolmont & Dr. Luca Caricchi.

University of Geneva

2022 Mapping the Sun's active regions from SDO images to HARPS-N solar spectra, (Astrophysics Laboratory project), The objective was to perform an analysis to determine if there's any individual contribution to the relative spectra driven by Sun's activity, Advisor: Dr. Michael Cretignier.

University of Geneva

2021 Searching for disintegrating planets in the TESS data, (Astrophysics Laboratory project), The objective was to optimize and implement a Python routine capable of identify asymmetrical light curves observed by TESS telescope, Advisor: Dr. Vincent Bourrier & Dr. Nathan Hara.

University of Geneva

- 2019 **Spectroscopy of rocky bodies of the Solar system: The Moon and Mars**, (*Thesis in Physics*), The objective was to identify the spectral signatures of the rock-forming minerals from the Moon and Mars with spectral data obtained at the astronomical observatory at University of Los Andes.
- 2018 **Episodic thermal convection in Enceladus Ice shell**, (*Thesis in Geosciences*), The objective was to run simulations in 2D/3D in order to study the heat behavior on the icy moon crust.

Computational skills

Advanced Python, JavaScript, html, p5js **Intermediate** C/C++, Fortran level lang.

OS Gnu/Linux, Windows.

Specialized IRAF, ArcGIS, Matlab, LaTeX, Geomatics, software CitcomS, ASPECT, BurnMan

Professional courses.

- 2018 **Astronomy, Astrometry, Astrophysics and Astrostatistics summer school**, University of Los Andes.
- 2017 **Seismic interpretation course**, European Association of Geoscientist and Engineers (EAGE).

DEI Leadership

- 2021-Current **Organizing committee member**, Mentoring program of the Colombian Astronomy Network of Students (RECA).
- 2019-Current **Organizing committee member**, *Conference series on the inclusion of women in astronomy*, Colombian network of women working on astroscience research. (CHIA).

Selected contributed talks

- 2019 European Rover Challenge, Competitor, Planet partner, Kielce, Poland.
- 2018 **IV** International conference on astrophysics & particle physics, <u>Speaker</u>, Chicago, US. **II** Latinamerican astrobiology congress, *Speaker*, National University of Colombia.

Job Experience

2020-2021 Geophysics GPR International Inc, Geophysicist Jr, Bogotá, Colombia.

Teaching assistant experience at the University of Los Andes

- 2019 Solid state physics and condensed matter, Physics Department.
- 2018 **Advanced seismology**, *Geosciences Department*.

Remote Sensing, SIG and GPS, Geosciences Department.

Introduction to observational astronomy, Physics Department.

Languages

Spanish Native

English Fluent

French B2 (DELF)